Guide to the John Wesley Blassingame Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Wesley Blassingame Papers
1857-1904
MS 737
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(3 boxes)
The John Wesley Blassingame Papers consist of note cards and research materials (electrostatic copies) used in the preparation of his dissertation, A Social and Economic History of the Negro in New Orleans (Yale University, 1971). Included are copies of reports of Louisiana state agencies, minutes and other papers of organizations like the White League of New Orleans, and legal documents deposited in the Orleans Parish courthouse.
Blassingame, John W., 1940-2000
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John W. Blassingame, 1972.
Scope and Contents
The John W. Blassingame Papers consist of electrostatic copies of reseach materials and note cards used in the preparation of Blassingame's 1971 Yale University Ph.D.,A Social and Economic History of the Negro in New Orleans, 1860-1880. The electrostatic copies may be divided into two groups. The first group includes various reports of the Louisiana government, minutes and other papers of organizations such as the White League of New Orleans and the Union League, and other miscellaneous items, all dating between 1864 and 1904. These papers were copied from originals at Tulane University and Louisiana State University. The second group of copies are succession papers copied from the Orleans Parish courthouse; they include wills, inventories of estates, marriage contracts, and similar items. The collection is completed by a series of note cards containing data on black property holders compiled from the 1850, 1860, and 1870 New Orleans manuscript census
Biographical / Historical
John Wesley Blassingame was born on March 23, 1940, in Covington, Georgia. He received a B.A. (1960) from Fort Valley State College, an M.A. (1961) from Howard University, and an M.Phil. (1968) and a Ph.D. (1971) from Yale University. Blassingame joined the Yale faculty in 1970. He served as the acting chairman of Afro-American studies (1971-1972, 1976-1977) and as chairman (1981-1989). In the mid-1970s, he also became the editor and publisher of the papers of Frederick Douglass. He wrote and edited numerous works on the history of slavery in America. Blassingame died in New Haven, Connecticut, on February 13, 2000.
Arrangement
The succession papers are arranged alphabetically by individual. The other papers are arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
African Americans -- History; Louisiana -- History; New Orleans (La.) -- History; Southern States; Historians; Blassingame, John W., 1940-2000; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory, 1857-1904; 1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Union League, New Orleans: constitution and by-laws, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flanders papers, 1864-1889 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Radical Republican Convention: report of the Committee on Grievances, 1867 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Delery, Dr. Charles, The Black Ghost or Radicalism in the United States, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Supervisors of Registration, Parish of Orleans: reports, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Crescent City White League of New Orleans: platform, [1868?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Assembly of Louisiana: "Report on the Conduct of the Late Elections and the Condition of Peace and Order in the State,", 1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hardin, J. Fair, Collection, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Special Investigating Committee of the Louisiana House of Representatives: report, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Special Louisiana House Committee, Session 1870--Charges against Gov. Warmoth: report (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brickell, Daniel Warren: papers, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Union League Club of America--4th Ward, New Orleans: minutes, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Allain, Hon. T.T.: oration delivered at West Baton Rouge, Louisiana, 1874 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Louisiana House of Representatives, Committee on Elections and Qualifications: report on the case of Charles Montaldo vs. C.L. Walker, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Campbell, Gen. Hugh J.: "The White League Conspiracy against Free Government" (address), 1875 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Kellogg, W.D.: papers, 1875-1876 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Returning Board of Louisiana," The Republic, Vol. VIII, No. 2, 1877 February (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Our New Orleans Letters--No. 2, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Secretary of State, State of Louisiana: annual report, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Secretary of State and State Librarian, State of Louisiana: annual report, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 19A)
  - Secretary of State, State of Louisiana: biennial report for the two years ending, May 1, 1882 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Secretary of State, State of Louisiana: biennial report, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ficklen, John R.: papers, 1894, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "A Few Specimen Depositions and Affidavits in the Case of Gov. Kellogg vs. Ex-gov. Warmoth...,", undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Succession papers
    - Anderson, Mary, 1860, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Azemard, Augustine, 1860, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Barber, Alexander E., 1870, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Beaulieu, Charlotte, 1870, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Blache, Marie Henriette Ernestine, 1870, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Bonseigrieur, Jean Baptiste Deterville, 1870, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Boutté, Francis, 1859, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Clay, John Francis, 1864, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Darensbourg, Victor, 1860, 1880 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Davenport, Nancy, 1860, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Dédé, Bazile, 1860, 1865, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Dreux, Gentilly, 1870, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - DuBois, Etienne, 1860, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Duplantier, Guy (Mrs.), 1870, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Fernandez, Ignace, 1870, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Foucher, Louis (Mrs.), 1861, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Furmeret, Louis (Mrs.), 1867, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Glaudin, Jean Baptiste, 1867, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Jacques, Pelagie, 1860, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Jason, Maria, 1860, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Lacroix, Francois, 1860, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Larche, Constance, 1869, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Laurens, Pierre, 1857, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Macarthy, Victor Eugene (Mrs.), 1870 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Macarty, Drausin B., 1860, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Macarty, Pauline, 1861, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Maindibourg, Octave, 1867, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Marigny, Celeste, 1860, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Montane, J.B., 1860, 1870, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Montford, Jean Jacques, 1860, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Narcisse, Edoward, 1867, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Pessou, Victor Martel, 1870, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Piron, Lirene (Emilie), 1860, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Reggio, Armand, 1860, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Rondeau, Mary, 1860, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Sauvé, Marie, 1867, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Taylor, William, 1860, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Tucker, Lucillia, 1860, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - List of Negroes in New Orleans Possessing $200 or More in Property
    - Data from 1850 census (Box 2)
    - Data from 1860 census (Box 2)
    - Data from 1870 census (Box 3)